Boker tov, today's דף *daf* is ס"ה *Samech Hei*, 65, and we're
going to pick up רב
יוסף בר חמא Rav Yosef bar Chama. *Rav Yosef bar Chama*. It's
about eight lines, ten lines from the bottom of ס"ו עמוד ב'
*Samech Vav Amud Bet*. There's an asterisk by the name רב יוסף
Rav Yosef? *Rav Yosef*. So the issue here, it's a משנה Mishna
*Mishnah*. The משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* is finally turning to the question about
a case where some type of a thing that the lender gets
back was not stipulated at the time of the deal, at least
that's a debate how to read the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah*. And nevertheless,
because he's getting some benefit, it's considered a type of ריבית ribbis.
*ribbit*. So the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* says after somebody lends a person
money, the person should not then go ahead and rent him something
at a discount, or, which is pretty straightforward, but then it also
says he should not go ahead and say, it also says that
the lender cannot live in the house of the borrower for free.
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* gets to a discussion in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* about well, is that normally something you would have to
pay for based on a whole discussion in בבא קמא Bava Kama,
*Bava Kamma* about זה נהנה וזה לא חסר zeh neheneh v'zeh lo
chaser *zeh nehene ve'zeh lo chaser* and so on. And the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says even if it's something you normally wouldn't have to
pay for, it's not acceptable here, it's a type of a ריבית
ribbis *ribbit*, which means that getting even a benefit that has not
that does not have a dollar value associated with it, it'd have
to be something that normally would cost anything, would be a problem,
which leads תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* to ask a question, which is, so
what does that mean? It means you can't do a favor for
the person who lent you money that you would normally do for
other
people? Maybe you can't do a favor that you wouldn't normally do,
but if it's a normal type of a thing you would do
for this person, all of a sudden now it's forbidden because he
lent you money? And תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says no, actually that would
be okay if it'd be a normal type of a favor. But
the point is that in the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* is either one
of two ways of reading it. Either that this is something that's
very public, so even though it really should be acceptable, when you
do him this favor let him stay in your house, when people
look at it, they perceive it as ריבית ribbis *ribbit*. Or the
other explanation תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* says is that it wasn't a favor,
that you didn't sort of say, "Hey come on, I'm not going
to be in my house, of course you can stay in my
house, I won't be there," it was something you'd normally do for
anybody else. The guy just decides to come and to house and
to squat and to take it. So in that case, even though
it's not something that you could collect from in court, but the
fact that he's taking it, that makes it a type of a
ריבית ribbis. *ribbit*. There he's sort of exercising his power and control
or that sort of reframes what exactly is happening. But that does
get to interesting questions about what types of things are now forbidden.
There's a whole question after you lend me money and I pay
you back and I say thank you. Is thank you ריבית ribbis
דברים *ribbit devarim* or is thank you just common courtesy? So yeah,
I know, but there's a discussion in some פוסקים *poskim* about that.
So anyway, that's interesting. So now we're going to sort of continue
with that theme. You had a question Rabbi Dov? That's okay. Okay,
so let's take a look now at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef. בר חמא תקיף עבדי דאינשי דמסיק בהו זוזי
*Rav Yosef bar Chama takif avde de-inshei de-masik lehu zuzie*. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef. בר חמא *Rav Yosef bar Chama* took up,
seized the slaves of certain people that owed him money, ועביד בהו
עבידתא *ve-avid behu avidta*, and he had them do work for him.
Certainly sounds like a type of a ריבית ribbis. *ribbit* to me
if he wasn't going to use that to discount off of the
debt.
But he said would that be okay?
Yeah, well that yes, that's another story. אמר ליה amar leh, רבא
Rava בריה *Amar lei Rava berei*. So רבא Rava *Rava*, his son,
said to him, מאי טעמא mai ta'ama, עביד מר הכי *Mai ta'ama
avid mar hachi*, why does the master do
such? Interesting he refers to the father as the master. Why does
the master do such? אמר ליה amar leh, *Amar lei*. אנא כרב
נחמן סבירא לי *Ana k-Rav Nachman sevira li*. I hold like רב
נחמן Rav Nachman? *Rav Nachman*. דאמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman *de-amar Rav
Nachman*, עבדא דאום כרסיה לא שוי *avda de-umkarsai lo shavei*. A slave
isn't even worth the bread of his stomach, meaning the money it
costs to feed a slave, you don't even get that much work
out of him. Which obviously reflects something about a society of people
who own slaves and attitudes and so on. But also obviously couldn't
be true because then it would economically make no sense to own
slaves.
Higher production economy like the United States display.
Exactly. So anyway, so I didn't really get anything out of him.
I got all I got back was the food that I paid,
not even that. So אמר ליה amar lei *Amar
lei*, he said to him, אימא דאמר רב נחמן Rav Nachman *eima
de-amar Rav Nachman*, when did רב נחמן Rav Nachman *Rav Nachman* say
that? כגון דרי עבדיה *kegon Dari avdei*, like Dari his servant. He
was talking about his servant. Or maybe what he means is he
was reacting to his servant. He might have been making a global
statement, but he basically was reacting to his servant. דמרקד בקובי *de-mirkid
be-kuvei*, that he basically dances in the bars. So he really he's
a big do-nothing clown. So that guy, עבדא אחרינא מי אמר *avda
achrina mi amar*? He wouldn't say it by other slaves. So alright,
so you really did get some benefit and it's a type of
a ריבית ribbis *ribbit*. So אמר ליה *Amar lei*, okay fine. אנא
כהא דרב דניאל בר רב
קטינא אמר רב *Ana ke-ha de-Rav Daniel bar Rav Katina amar Rav*.
I hold like this position of רב דניאל *Rav Daniel* in the
name of רב *Rav*. Yeah. So what? רב דניאל *Rav Daniel*? Yeah,
I've never seen that.
Yeah, it is, it's not so common.
דאמר התוקף עבדו של חבירו ועשה בו מלאכה פטור *de-amar ha-takif avdo
shel chaveiro ve-asa bo melacha patur*. That if you seize your friend's
slave and you do מלאכה *melacha*, you're exempt. Why? It's a similar
type of a discussion about
what we'll see, but could be talking about זה נהנה וזה לא
חסר zeh neheneh v'zeh lo chaser, *zeh nehene ve'zeh lo chaser*, assuming
that the slave is not doing other work. at that same time.
So but the גמרא Gemara says the reason is דניחא ליה דלא
ליסתרי עבדיה, d'nicha leh d'lo nistaryei avdei, because somebody wouldn't want you
to, you know, not make his slave, allow the slave to become,
what's the word,
not lazy, but there's a word that's on the tip of my
tongue. Yeah, anyway, it's fine. You don't want your slave anyway to
learn to become lazy and to, you know, and so therefore exactly,
you gotta keep on working them, you know, so again, it's a
really interesting attitude here from a slave-owning society. As soon as the
slave is taking a break, we gotta go ahead and you know,
then you're spoiling them, indulging them, gotta make them work, it's always
you know, you're benefiting them, you're not teaching them to be, what's
the word, insolent? What's the word, anyway, not to be lazy. Indolent.
Indolent,
yeah I think that was what I was looking for, indolent. Anyway,
so אמר ליה, ah, so you see, so bottom line is, is
that you really like it's, you know, you're not, you're not, the
master would want you to do this. You're doing him a favor
by working his slave during the slave's coffee break. Okay? So אמר
ליה, he said back to him, הני מילי היכא דלא מסיק ביה
זוזי, hani milei heicha d'lo masik bei zuzei, maybe you could make
that argument if the guy doesn't owe you money. So then you
could try to apply, I don't know, a זה נהנה וזה לא
חסר type of a case, okay, or the master would be okay
with it. מר כיון דמסיק ביה זוזי מיחזי כרבית. mar keivan d'masik
bei zuzei michezi k'ribis.
But you, now that he owes you money, it looks like רבית,
ribis, even if technically speaking, you know, this is not some, something
that you would be allowed to do, in this context it's wrong.
דאמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן אע"פ שאמרו הדר בחצר
חבירו שלא מדעתו אינו צריך להעלות לו שכר, d'amar רב יוסף בר
מניומי Rav Yosef bar Minyumi אמר רב נחמן amar Rav Nachman אע"פ
שאמרו הדר בחצר חבירו שלא מדעתו אינו צריך להעלות לו שכר af
al pi she'amru hadar b'chatzeir chaveiro shelo mida'ato eino tzarich le'haalos lo
sachar, in an explanation of our משנה mishna clarifying our משנה, Mishna!
that even though normally if you're living in a guy's house without
his permission, you don't have to pay him if it's a case
of זה נהנה וזה לא חסר, if it's a house that he
normally wouldn't rent out, okay, so even though that's true, הלוהו ודר
בחצירו צריך להעלות לו שכר, halvahu v'dar b'chatzeiro tzarich le'haalos lo sachar,
after you lent him money and you go ahead and want to
live in his house, צריך להעלות לו שכר, tzarich le'haalos lo sachar,
you have to pay him, okay, because then it really does look
like רבית. ribis. You just deducted down the loan, right?
Well,
sure, you could always do that. אמר ליה הדרי בי. amar leh
hadri bi. He says, ah, fine, you're right, okay, I retract. All
right, so the son got the father to retract, to acknowledge that
he was not acting appropriately there. But again, it's interesting, right? Because
it's saying that it's not something that normally has a dollar, you
know, it's something that the person could sue for reimbursement in court,
so you could argue therefore it is not considered something of value
that you received, and nevertheless in this context it's wrong. תוספות Tosfos
says one of two reasons, either it's public. Using a slave, dwelling
in a house is public. If it was something maybe a little
bit more private, it maybe wouldn't be an issue. Or what really
also seems really about these cases here is you, the lender, on
your initiative are seizing it. So that obviously makes it a much
bigger deal, right? If I go ahead and I normally, you know,
lend, do favors for my friends and let my slaves are, you
know, have their break, if you need to use my slave to
rake your yard, I'll say sure, not a problem, or whatever, you
know, and that's the normal type thing I do, that might be
okay even after you lent me money, because that's just, you know,
it's not seen in the context of lending money, it would be
a normal thing. But here it is not, you know, you went
and you took it. And particularly thinking about the fact that you
know, the lender always has this power dynamic over the borrower, right?
עבד לוה לאיש מלוה, eved loveh l'ish malveh, so also exerting that
power dynamic just forcefully, taking it, is part of what makes this
problematic, yeah.
Is this the same רבא Rava like רבא Rava, we always come
up with as in אביי Abayei and רבא Rava or is it
a different רבא, Rava the son of רב יוסף?
I'm not sure. I didn't think רבא Rava was the son of
רב יוסף. רבא Rava was a student of רב יוסף. So, maybe,
well there's רב יוסף בר חמא. Right, yeah, I don't know. He's
one of, yeah I don't know, I'm not good at that, I
don't know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says like this, okay let's
keep on going. אמר אביי האי מאן דמסיק זוזי דריביתא בחבריה. amar
Abayei hai man d'masik zuzei d'ribisa b'chavreih. Okay, now this is fascinating,
we're now going to have a couple of discussions about somebody who
actually has lent money and is charging interest. So, you know, it's
like, it's an interesting comment like, like if you're learning כשרות, kashrus,
right, you don't normally have a גמרא Gemara discussing about like what
do we do about, you know, in practice people that are eating
בשר בחלב? basar b'chalav? What do we do about people that are
eating חזיר? chazir? No, what do we do about people that are
מחלל שבת? mechalel Shabbos? Like, there's places where you find the גמרא
gemara, sort of acknowledge the phenomenon of a regular violation of a
מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so you have it by שמיטה, shmita, right, by
שמיטה shmita clearly you're dealing with a whole series of תקנות takanos
about עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz and whatever, and people that don't keep
שמיטה shmita and so on. Okay, so it's also interesting in the
case of רבית, ribis, right, you have this sense about, I mean
I guess we had it by בבא קמא, we had people who
stole and we were dealing about תקנת השבים takanas hashavim and תקנות
takanos for returning, you know, stolen objects and so on. So there
we were also acknowledging the phenomenon of, you know, violation and of
theft. So here too, right,
right, so here too we acknowledge the phenomenon of people that lend
with רבית. ribis. So let's take a look.
האי מסיק זוזי hai masik zuzei is the lender?
מסיק זוזי masik zuzei means somebody who is now collecting money back
from a loan that he had given?
Yeah, so the before the phrase was... that's what I always get
confused with these... yeah, so the phrase was before אינשי דמסיק בהו
זוזי, inshi d'masik behu zuzei, which is people that he had lent
money to. So מסיק masik now is to lend. Okay, so here
is the lender, right? So, so here האי מאן דמסיק זוזי דרביתא
בחבריה hai man d'masik zuzei d'rabisa b'chavre somebody is charging interest on
a loan, lent money to his friend in interest. וכאזלי חיטי ארבע
גריווי בזוזא v'ka'azli chitei arba givuyei b'zuza and grain is going for
four units for a
zuz. Okay, בשוקא, b'shuka, that's the standard price in the marketplace. ויהיב
ליה חמשה. v'yaiv leihu chamsha. Now, basically here's the story. This guy
owed Shimon owed Reuven רבית ribis on a loan and the רבית,
ribis, the interest charged, was a zuz. Okay. So to pay his
interest which Shimon paid Reuven was not four units of wheat, which
is what the marketplace is for which goes for a zuz, but
five units of wheat. Okay, so he overpaid the interest, alright? So
he paid the interest with something worth a little more than a
zuz.
Did he overpay the interest or did he pay back the loan?
No, he overpaid the interest. No, this is the interest payment. So
כי מפקינן מיניה ki mafkinan minei now the הלכה halacha as you
might remember before the question was is רבית קצוצה יוצאה בדיינים? ribis
ketzuza yotze b'dayanim? Okay, if when it's real רבית דאורייתא, ribis d'oraisa,
it's in the contract, it's made explicit, here are the terms of
the loan: you are borrowing whatever, each week you have to pay
me an extra one zuz per week interest, that's רבית קצוצה, ribis
ketzuza, it's explicit in the loan, it's an איסור דאורייתא. issur d'oraisa.
And the question was can now the borrower go to court to
get his interest back. Okay, so there was a debate. It had
to do with to what degree is רבית ribis like a type
of a ממונות mamonus issue or more of an איסור issur issue.
The הלכה halacha was, well it wasn't clear what the הלכה halacha
was, but we're going to פסקן pasken and what's implicit in this
story is it is יוצאה בדיינים, yotze b'dayanim, you can go ahead
and get the interest amount, the interest payment back. Okay, so this
guy he owes a zuz in רבית. ribis. He pays something worth
a zuz and a quarter. He pays five units of grain, not
four units of grain. And now he's coming to get his רבית
ribis back. Okay, he goes to court and he wants to get
his רבית ribis back. Do we give him back a zuz or
do we give him back his five units of grain, which is
more than a zuz? Because the contract only obligated him to pay
a zuz and he paid a zuz and a quarter. So how
much now can he get back when he's retrieving his interest? Okay,
so that's the question. ויהיב
ליה חמשה כי מפקינן מיניה v'yaiv leihu chamsha ki mafkinan minei when
we extract the רבית ribis from the lender, ארבע
מפקינן מיניה, arba mafkinan minei, so we only take back four because
that was the only thing that was the real רבית ribis payment.
אידך, idach, the other one, אוזולי הוא דקא מוזיל גביה, ozulei hu
d'ka m'ozil gabei, he just discounted it to him meaning it wasn't
technically a רבית ribis payment, it was like a gift, or he
was assessing
the wheat more cheaply. He said, I'll give you a bargain, these
five units of wheat we'll consider it just a dollar and that'll
be, so I'm charging as it were less for my wheat. But
at the end of the day, he only gave him a zuz.
That's how he priced the wheat as a zuz, so he only
gave him the רבית ribis payment, so he only gets back a
zuz. רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says, no,
חמשה
מפקינן מיניה, chamsha mafkinan minei, no, we take back all five units
דמעיקרא אדעתא דרביתא אתא לידיה d'me'ikara ad'ata d'ribisa asa l'yadei that in
the end of the day he was giving it in as רבית
ribis payment. He might have given a little more or whatever but
nevertheless he was sort of treating it as רבית ribis payment, so
therefore he gets it all back. Okay, ואמר אביי v'amar Abaye and
Abaye says, האי מאן דמסיק ארבע זוזי דרביתא בחבריה, hai man d'masik
arba zuzei d'ribisa b'chavrei, a guy sort of has owed to him
four zuz of רבית, ribis, four zuz of interest, ויהיב ליה גלימא
בגוייהו v'yaiv lei glima b'gavaihu and the borrower gives a coat, okay,
which worth obviously worth more than four zuz. כי מפקינן מיניה ארבע
מפקינן מיניה גלימא לא מפקינן מיניה.
ki mafkinan
minei
arba mafkinan minei glima lo mafkinan minei. Now when the guy comes
to court to sue for his interest payments back, we give him
back four dollars, we don't give him back the cloak, because only
four dollars worth of the cloak was the interest payment. The rest
was like a gift or who knows what. But since again part
of the point is, it should be pointed out that it is
רבית קצוצה ribis ketzuza which is יוצאה בדיינים. yotze b'dayanim. It is
explicit, the explicit רבית ribis in the contract to which you can
go ahead and get paid back from in court. So therefore Abaye
is saying the only קצוצה ketzuza part of it is the four
zuz, right? Anything else was not part of the contractual obligation of
רבית, ribis, so therefore you cannot retrieve that. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
no, גלימא מפקינן מיניה, glima mafkinan minei, no, we give back the
entire coat. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, כי היכי דלא לימרו גלימא דמיכסי
וקאי גלימא דרביתא הוא. ki heichi d'lo leimru glima d'michasi v'kai glima
d'ribisa hu. Now, here he doesn't say that you can really say
that this was fully the רבית ribis payment, it was way disproportionate
of the four dollars, so maybe it's like you can't say that
within the context of the contract this was the four dollars. Clearly
it was excessive of the four dollars. But there's still a perception
issue, right? People will go ahead and see the guy wearing the
day ago I had a nice coat and then they see this
guy wearing this nice coat and says, oh yeah, that's because it
was a interest coat that he's wearing. So therefore even if they
would know
that, they'd say, alright, maybe he just took it in for
a little more, maybe they're for the payment. Right, that's a good
question. How do people know the exact context? But presumably if this
guy is like known that he's lending money with interest, which he
presumably is and now I'm starting to sue for court and then
they see him wearing my nice coat. Okay, but of course then
you could say that I can that if I gave him my
coat in payment of the loan, he should have to so it's
true, it assumes that people sort of know everybody else's business. All
right. Anyway, but this case it seems that רבא Rava more concedes
that it clearly is outside of the technical payment of ריבית.
ribbis
Right,
but there the differences were smaller. Okay, and there it was more,
it seems like רבא Rava was more saying we could say that
that's just how he's pricing the wheat and it is technically all
the ריבית ribbis payment. Here there's an acknowledgment that it's clearly not
more than the ריבית ribbis. payment, but nevertheless there's a perception issue.
Listen, fine, but let's say it was like you know, instead of
a nice, you know, Armani suit it was like I understand.
Right. Right, it was something that was,
it's something that wasn't
public but at the same time was clearly excessive. Would there, would
there you have to give back the whole object or could he
keep the difference? So רמב"ם Rambam seems to rule that it's not
how public it is, that if you give an object even if
it's worth more, then you have to give back the whole object,
which seems to be רבא's Rava general gist here. But if you
read the specific justification רבא Rava is giving, it seems a little
more specific than that.
You think that that's רבא's Rava gist when he says דלא לימרו?
dela leimru?
No, no, here, but the fact that in both cases he says
if he gave five you give back all five, if he gave
a coat you give back the coat. So the question is like
what you know, could you try to find a case that fell
between the two or is רבא's Rava general attitude here that you
just give it all back? Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like
this. I'm sorry.
Basically, if he gives something clearly in excess, no matter you know
how public it is
or how private it is, you would, that's the way רמב"ם Rambam
seems to rule. אמר רבא האי מאן דמסיק תריסר זוזי דריביתא בחבריה.
Amar Rava hai man dumasik treisar zuzey deribisa bechavrei.
Somebody has 12, you know, owed to him of 12 zuz of
interest. ואוגר ליה חצר דמיתגרא בעשרה ואוגריה ניהליה בתריסר. Veoger lei chatzar
demisgara beasara veogrei nihalei betreisar.
So basically, okay, so here I am charging Charlie
$12 of interest on $100 and what Charlie does to me, what
Charlie does is, oh no, what I do now, oh let me
see if I get this right. What Charlie does is...
wait so what...
Charlie owes me $12 of ריבית. Ribbit Charlie's got a nice house.
A month is what he has to pay me. Charlie's got a
nice house and I want to and I want to live in
it. Okay, he has a rental house. That rental house only goes
for $10 a month. But Charlie says to me, you know what,
Dov, let's make the price $12 a month, okay, and therefore you'll
stay in it each month and that'll be my interest payment to
you. Okay, it's a good win-win situation as long as I don't
mind charging interest. Okay, so Charlie doesn't have to pay me the
full $12, he gives me the, what we're going to value at
$12, even though it normally sells for
10. Okay. ואוגריה ניהליה בתריסר. Veogrei nihalei betreisar. Now Charlie, who's very
smart, he comes back like at the end of the year or
whatever, the end of the month, and he goes, takes me to
court and he says, okay, I was paying you an interest payment.
I have a right to retrieve the interest payment if I can
get the court to you know, deal with the case or whatever.
So now you got to give me back my interest payment. How
much do I have to give Charlie back? $10 or $12?
Yeah, you see? We valued it at $12 so it was יצא
yotei the interest payment, right? But it normally goes for 10. So
maybe I can say I only got a $10 benefit from him
as my... so if I'm going to give it back to him,
I'm going to give him $10. So let's take a look. כי
מפקינן מיניה תריסר מפקינן מיניה. Nope,
since we value that that rent at $12 and that was interest
payment, now that I got that month's rent, I now have to
pay Charlie $12 when I'm giving him back his ריבית Ribbit. I
have to pay $12 for the rent. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי
לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Acha miDifti leRavina. So רב אחא מדפתי Rav
Acha miDifti said to רבינא, Ravina, ולומר ליה כי אגרא הכי גבי
קא משתרשי לי? velimar lei ki agra hachi gabei ka mishtarshi lei?
I was renting it at that rate at $12, I agreed to
a higher rate, because anyway it was all profit for me. It
was all my ריבית. ribbis. So I was willing to give him
a little bit of an excessive rate. השתא Hashta now, that you're
making me give up my interest payment, you know, דלא משתרשי לי,
dela mishtarshi lei, I'm not sort of getting benefit out of it,
כדאגרי כולי עלמא אגרינא. ke'dagri kulei alma agrina.
So, you know, I I should I should be considered like any
normal person, it should be considered a $10 that I got from
Charlie, a $10 value for his ריבית ribbis payment. So he didn't
pay his full ריבית ribbis. payment, he gave me something worth $10.
So I'll give him back $10. Okay,
no, אמר ליה סברת וקבלת. savart vekibalt. No,
you understood the terms and you accepted the terms. So you were
willing to value it at $12, you considered it a $12 benefit
that you received, so you received according to your
agreement $12 of value for your ריבית ribbis payment, so you have
to give him back $12 of value. Okay, which is we don't
have that much רחמנות rachmanus for the people that are lending with
ריבית. ribbis. I mean, it's somewhat consistent, it's not the same case,
but it's consistent with רבא before. The guy gave him something excessive,
when he gets it back, he gets the full amount back. Yes.
So since all these, all these עניינים inyanim have to do now
with ריבית קצוצה ribbis ketzutza etc.
I hope
at some point before the end of the פרק, perek, like every
interest-bearing loan with a bank...
Right. Sure.
That's why, that's the whole idea of היתר עסקה. Heter Iska. Either
you do it with a non-Jewish bank, or if you're living in
Israel, you do a היתר עסקה. Heter Iska.
So yeah, I get it, but it's the first time היתר עסקה
Heter Iska I said that out loud.
I understand.
We'll get to it before finding the right moment to explain how
that works. Right. Yeah. Sure. Yeah. Why isn't the borrower held in
some amount of responsibility?
Because he also עובר over on the law. Right.
So that might be why so, you know, again, you could read
all of this as not being, you know, like, you know,
giving a penalty to the lender but just trying to assess how
do we identify what the ריבית ribbis is, although as I said,
it does seem like we are tipped in favor of looking at
it, you know, looking at it favorably from the perspective of the
borrower and not of the lender. But look, I would basically say
that I think that there tends to be a what do you
call it, like a certain sympathy. Like yes, you were עובר over
on a law, but you know, you you had to put food
on the table, you know. So if those were your only options,
so right, obviously, and the other person is taking advantage of people
in a, you know, in a weak position. Alright, so let's take
a look at the משנה. mishna. מרבין על השכר ואין מרבין על
המכר. Marbin al hasachar ve'ein marbin al hamacher. Okay, so מרבין על
השכר ואין מרבין על המכר. Marbin al hasachar ve'ein marbin al hamacher.
You can increase the rental payment, but you cannot increase the price.
This is getting back to the types of issues we've been talking
about until now in which it is either delayed delivery or delayed
payment. This would be a case of delayed payment. So if you're
going to pay later for something you got, so we don't want
you to be paying more when you're paying later because then it
is like an interest payment because you let me hold on to
my money longer after I received the goods, I'm going to give
you some extra money. Right? So that's a type of a ריבית.
ribbis. I'm holding on to my own money and I should have
given it to you so and so therefore and now when I'm
going to give it to you later, I'll give you extra. So
that's why you cannot when you have a deferred payment for a
sale, you cannot charge extra, but when you have a deferred payment
for a rental, you can. So what's the difference? So the משנה
mishna, will describe a case and then the גמרא Gemara will describe
why. So כיצד, Keitzad, how is this true? השכיר לו את חצרו.
Hiskir lo et chatzeiro. You rent your yard, your house to somebody.
ואמר לו, Ve'amar lo, אם מעכשיו אתה נותן לי הרי הוא לך
בעשרה סלעים. Im me'achshav ata noten li harei hu lecha be'asara sla'im.
If you want to pay me now for the year, ten dollars
for the year. לשנה, Leshana, for the year. ואם של חודש בחודש,
Ve'im shel chodesh bechodesh,
but if you want to pay me on a monthly basis, סלע
לחודש, Sela lechodesh, it'll be a dollar a month. מותר. Mutar. That's
allowed even though, presumably, you're saying if you pay me later it'll
go up twenty percent. That's allowed. Okay. מכר לו את השדה, Machar
lo et hasadeh, ואמר לו, Ve'amar lo, now if you're selling the
field and you say to him, אם מעכשיו אתה נותן לי הרי
היא שלך באלף זוז, Im me'achshav ata noten li harei hi shelcha
be'elef zuz, if you want to pay me now, it'll go for
a thousand dollars. Okay.
I'm sorry. Yes.
If לגורן, Legoren, if you want to wait till the time of
the threshing floor, you want to wait till after the wheat grows
and you thresh it and you sell it and then you'll have
more cash available. So I would understand you don't have the cash
on you right now, you want to wait for a half a
year till you can sell the produce and get the cash, but
you want me to wait half a year as well. So if
you want us to wait till that time, בשנים עשר מנה, Bishneim
asar maneh, it'll cost you twelve hundred dollars. אסור, Assur, that's forbidden.
So both cases it's deferred payment, in one case you can charge
more, in the other case you can't. Yes?
This is pretty exactly the situation of like car payments or a
mortgage.
Right? Pay it all up front or we'll do it on financing.
And the whole financing is exactly that. It's basically like, we'll lend
you the money and then you're going to pay us interest payments
because effectively we have lent you the money.
Right.
So that's exactly what car payments are. Right, when you're paying interest,
why are you separately paying interest? Because they've basically have said you
bought this car for twenty thousand dollars, you're not paying me, so
we're lending you the twenty thousand dollars and now you're going to
pay it back later with interest. So that's exactly that. That's what
deferred payment is.
Can't take a mortgage out on a house from a bank that's
owned by where the CEO is Jewish.
I don't know if it's about the CEO. That gets to do
with questions about corporate ownership and who's the owner and who are
you borrowing from when you borrow from a corporation.
Okay. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מאי שנא רישא
ומאי שנא סיפא. Mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa. What is the
difference between purchase and rental? So I think you could probably answer
that question. Why do you think by when I pay monthly by
the apartment that's okay but when I pay when I pay the
deferred payment by the field it's not okay? Can you think of
the answer? No. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. רבא ורב
יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rava ve'Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu, שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא
בסוף. Schirut eina mishtalemet ela besof.
Because you're only
obligated to pay a month's rent at the end of the month.
You only received the goods, if you want to think about it
that way. What goods did I receive when I'm renting the apartment?
I received the use of the apartment. So I only receive the
goods if we can conceptualize those as month units, I can receive
the goods at the end of the month. Okay. So therefore the
actual amount that it costs is defined by the baseline is defined
by how much would you pay when you were paying at the
end of the month. at the end when you paid at the
end of the month. And therefore when I charge you less when
you pay upfront, what I'm doing is I'm giving you a discount
by paying early. So the difference is are you charging more for
paying late? That's ריבית. ribbis. Are you charging less for paying early?
That's permitted. So therefore what you have to decide is well what
is the baseline? When should it be paid? And then you'll figure
out whether what you're doing is postponing the payment or whether you
are paying early. So by a transaction, by a purchase, you pay
at the time of the purchase. So if I let you pay
later for the field, we're postponing it and you're paying more for
paying late. By rent, you pay at the end of the month,
at the end of the year. And if you pay upfront, then
what I'm doing is because you're paying early I'm giving you a
discount and that's permitted. What was your question Michael?
I was gonna say is that the difference is the way we
do it now
for rent is always payable beginning of the month. No one waits
till the end and pays.
Right, with
first because you ask for first month's rent upfront. Right, that's true.
That's a good point. But I still but still it would probably
be month by month. So if you were to pay upfront.
You're always paying in
advance though is my point. Yes, but if I pay for the
year, I'm still paying eleven out of those twelve months early. So
that could still work. Okay? So שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא לבסוף. Sechirus
eina mishtalemes ela levasof. Is that a מחלוקת machlokes also whether... Well,
I'll get to that. שכירות אינה משתלמת לבסוף. Sechirus eina mishtalemes levasof.
והאי, V'hai, this guy, כיון דלא מטא זמניה למגבי, keivan d'lo mata
zamnei lemigbei, since time hasn't come yet to collect, we're getting a
year's payment upfront, לאו אגר נטר ליה. lav agar natar lei.
He is not getting that that phrase אגר נטר, agar natar, שכר
schar for the postponement, שכר schar for postponing the payment. No, what
you're getting is a discount for paying early. Okay? לאו אגר נטר
ליה. lav agar natar lei. משוה הוא דהכי שויא. Mashvehu dehachi shavei.
That's
the baseline is a dollar a month. Based the baseline is what
you would pay when you paid at the end of the month.
והאי דאמר ליה מאה ועתה תן לי תשעים או עשרה סלעים, Vehai
d'amar lei me'ah ve'atah ten li tish'im o asara sla'im, and now
if he's saying if you pay me upfront for the year I'll
give it to you for ten, לשנה, leshana, אוזולי הוא דקא מוזיל
גביה. ozolei hu d'ka mozil gabei.
He's giving him a discount. So discount's okay. Discount for early payment
is okay. Exception, you know, an additional fee for late payment, that's
not good. סיפא, Seifa, the end, by a sale, כיון דזביני נינהו,
keivan d'zvini ninhu, since it's a purchase, ובעי למשקל דמי מעכשיו, uba'ei
lemishkal dmei me'achshav, and you're entitled to get paid right now, הלכך,
hilkach, and but you say if you're paying me later it will
be more, הלכך אגר
נטר ליה הוא, hilkach agar natar lei hu, you're getting money for
postponing the payment. הוא. hu. ואסור, V'asur, and it's forbidden. Very nice
גמרא, Gemara very straightforward. Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so Rava says,
דקו רבנן בהא מילתא, daku rabanan beha milta, the rabbis looked closely
into this thing or read the text closely regarding this matter, ואשכחו
קרא, v'ashkechu kra, and they found this idea that שכירות, sechirus, that
rental comes at the end is based on a פסוק. pasuk. What's
the פסוק? pasuk? כשכיר שנה בשנה, Kisechir shana b'shana,
like the rental of a year by year. So שכירות שנה של
זו, Sechirus shana shel zo, the rental for this year, אינה משתלמת
אלא בשנה אחרת, eina mishtalemes ela b'shana acheres, is paid really at
the end in the other year. שנה בשנה. Shana b'shana. Somehow it
means... Does that... How do you know it doesn't mean this year's
paid during this year? Anyway, somehow they read the פסוק pasuk to
mean this year is paid at the beginning of next year. Fine.
Now Michael asks the question, isn't there a whole debate ישנה לשכירות
מתחילה ועד סוף yeshna l'sechirus mitechila v'ad sof or אינה לשכירות אלא
לבסוף? eina l'sechirus ela levasof? So תוספות Tosafot deals with that. So
תוספות Tosafot says yeah, but that's the question about when do you
incur your debt to me. Are you incurring your debt like every
day, every minute, or are you incurring your debt at the end
of the period? But תוספות Tosafot says even if you're incurring your
debt to me every minute, it only is payable at the end
of the month or at the end of however you define the
unit, right? Some things have a unit of a month, some things
a year, some things a week. Okay? But the point is you
might be owing me that money, but it's not yet due. It's
not payable until the end of the period, and therefore if you
pay upfront, you are actually getting a discount for paying early rather
than a charge for paying late. Okay? So now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
And based on this you can make this, you know, agreement with
your, let's say you have a day laborer. Pay me in the
beginning of the morning, you know, I'll pay you a little less
than if I pay at the end of the day.
Yeah. Sure. Exactly. Okay. ואם לגורן בשנים עשר מנה אסור. Ve'im legoren
bishneim asar mane asur. And if it now and now, so this
is the end of the משנה, mishna. right? If you want to
wait till the end of the up to to the season to
the, you know, that it's that you can sell the wheat, then
it'll be twelve hundred dollars if you want to wait, that's forbidden,
then it's a charge for for paying late.
אגר נטר Agar natar means postponed payment.
שכר המתנה Schar hamtana or שכר שמירה, schar shmira, but שמירה, shmira,
holding on to the money. Yes. So it's a piece of extra
of a fee for postponing the payment. אמר רב נחמן, טרשא שרי.
Amar Rav Nachman Tarsha shari. Now this is very funny. טרשא Tarsha
means basically a fee for paying late is permissible. Like even though
the משנה mishna just said it's forbidden. Okay. Jastrow says that the
word טרשא tarsha sort of means like a little bit has the
word comes from has the word דש dash in it. What does
it mean דש? dash? It means that you are
not...
There's the word דש dash in it. I don't know, I haven't
looked at the etymology. But anyway that that somehow the actual meaning
of the word is like a the somehow anyway he says that
the point is רש"י Rashi just says that this is what the
context is, but Jastrow says it's something in the etymology of the
word is that you're not being explicit about it. Let's say there's
an later charge for paying late, but you say but you're not
saying it explicitly. What you're saying is... is the following: You're saying,
how much is this field? Okay, now it's known that it's a
thousand acres and it would normally go for a thousand dollars. Okay,
that's known by the standard market price. So you don't, how much
is this field? He'll say, well I'll tell you what, if you
want to pay me in six months from now, when are you
going to pay me? Six months from now? Okay, the field is
1200 dollars. So I never said it's a thousand dollars, but if
you want to wait and do it later it's 1200. I said
the price is 1200 dollars. You're going... if you're going to be
paying me six months from now, the price is 1200 dollars. For
you, 1200 dollars. Okay,
so that's permissible because it is not being framed as a late
payment even though I am, you know, incorporating that חשבון cheshbon into
how I'm setting the price. That's a bit of a חידוש, chiddush,
right?
One second, you could have said the price six months from now
is 1200 dollars and the price now is 1000 dollars, that's okay?
No. As soon as you say the price now is 1000, you
are framing the 1200 as a late payment. But if all you,
right, right, but yes, you don't have to say it's going to
be a late payment. If you say it's 1000 now, 1200 later,
that's אסור. assur.
And then let's say, okay for mine, price six months from now
is 1200 dollars. You say all right, what if I pay you
now? He'll say all right, 1000. Can I do that?
Maybe but maybe once you did that, then it's now אסור assur
to do the other thing. Yes.
What about where it's not like a fee for paying later that
we all agreed to, but like you don't pay on time? Like
there's late fees everywhere for...
Ah, yes. So let's say it's like a rental and it's due
at the end of the month and it comes the end of
the month and now you're... so that's an interesting question. Can it
be basically
like more like a penalty, penalty as opposed to like an interest?
That's interesting. I mean I would assume that it's at least a
problem of ריבית דרבנן. ribbis d'rabbanan. It looks like ריבית ribbis and
whatever. But I understand how conceptually it's a different thing. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב
נחמן Amar Rav Nachman, טרשא שרי. tarsha shari. Okay, now the גמרא's
Gemara going to say when is it considered, when does it become
explicit that it is a higher amount. But he says if you
just say it's 1200 dollars, that's fine, and it's not clear that
that's in contrast to 1000 dollars. איתיבי רמי בר חמא לרב נחמן.
Eisivei Rami bar Chama l'Rav Nachman. Rami bar Chama told Rav Nachman,
and they read it רב עוקבא בר חמא לרב נחמן. Rav Ukva
bar Chama l'Rav Nachman. ואם לגורן בשמונים ובמנה אסור. Ve-im lagoren b'shmonim
u'v'mna assur. What do you mean? It's a משנה! mishna. If you're
charging more for at the end of, you know, six months, it's
forbidden. אמר ליה התם קצלי הכא לא קצלי. Amar lei hasam katzlei
hacha lo katzlei. No,
there he made it explicit. He like, he cut the price. He
said 1200 here, you know, 1000 here, 1200 later. If you're just
completely, you know, if you're just setting a price and you're not
in contrast to a different price, then that's just the price. Okay?
So if you just say oh you're going to pay me in
six months, the price is 1200, that would be okay. אמר רב
פפא טרשא דידי שרי. Amar Rav Pappa Tarsha didi shari. My late
payment is permissible. He was a... he was
into the beer business. Okay, מאי טעמא, Mai taama? why? שכראי לא
פסיד shecharai lo passit because basically the way רש"י Rashi explains it
is the following: He goes ahead, I'll be Rav Pappa, I go
ahead and I sell beer now, it's in תשרי. Tishrei. Now the
market is low, okay, it's a dollar a barrel. Okay, if we
waited till ניסן Nisan or whatever it would be a dollar fifty
a barrel. So I go ahead and I sell it to Michael
at a dollar... Michael's going to pay me in six months from
now when the market's high. Okay, so he buys it from me
now and I'm going to sell it... and he's going to pay
me in six months and I sell it to him at a
dollar fifty a barrel. So I'm selling it to him at a
higher rate, okay, and he's going to pay me later. The higher
rate than it's worth right now. Okay, so but he says that's
permissible. Why? טרשא דידי שרי. tarsha didi shari. Why is that permissible?
מאי טעמא שכראי
לא פסיד. mai ta'ama shecharai lo passit. My beer will not spoil.
I don't... Michael's not doing me any favors, okay, by giving me
extra paying it later. I could just as easily put my beer
in storage, sell it six months from now at exactly that price,
a dollar and a half. So I'm not getting anything from the
fact that Michael is buying it now and going to pay me
later because I could just as easily store it and sell it
later for exactly that same price. Okay, שכראי לא פסיד. shecharai lo
passit. זוזי לא צריכנא. zozei lo tzarichna.
It's not like I am hard up for money that I therefore,
you know, am pressured to doing the sale and to agreeing to
the sale now or anything like that. I'm wealthy, so בקיצור be-kitzur
I could just wait. So therefore since I could just wait, the
fact that he's paying me, you know, at the later price is
going to be... is not, you know, is not really doing me
any benefits later. So
the גמרא Gemara says: אנן דקעבידנא מלתא גבי לוקח. anu d'ka-avidna miltah
gabei lokeiach. I'm just doing good business, okay, for you know. So
therefore that's fine by me because it's not really... it's not like
I am losing out because I don't have the money now and
I needed the money now. That's his point, that I don't need
the money. Normally, like the explanation of why should you be paying
me interest is because I don't have access to my... to that
money. But he's saying I don't need the money, I'm wealthy, so
it's not like I'm asking him to pay me because he's not
giving me use of that money. It's not like I couldn't sell
it myself at that price six months from now. So from my
perspective, I'm not really, you know, it's not really like
it's... like like it's like he's doing me any big favor. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, so the answer back is let's take
a look at the answer back. So אמר רב ששת בריה דרב
אידי לרב פפא, Amar Rav Sheshet's brei de-Rav Idi le-Rav Pappa, מאי
חזית מר דקא אזלת בתר דידך? mai chazei mar deka azlat batar
didach? Who lets you see this, you know, this through your lens?
Okay, you say, eh, for me I could have just waited, no
big deal, he's paying me extra now, I could have sold it
later anyway. זיל בתר דידהו! Zil batar dideihu! Go by poor Michael
over here! דאילו הוו להו זוזי, Di-ilu havu lehu zuzei, if Michael
had cash on hand, שקלי כהשתא, shakli ke-hashta, he would be paying
today's prices, a dollar. השתא דלית להו זוזי, Hashta deleis lehu zuzei,
and now because he doesn't have cash on hand, שקלו כיוקרא דקמי,
shaklu kiyukra dalkamei, he has to be paying a dollar and a
half. So he has to be paying more because he doesn't have
available cash. So that's what רבית ribbis is. The guy the borrower
doesn't have available cash so he's paying, you know, more than he
would normally pay because of his because of his need of money.
So it's actually interesting, it goes back to the beginning of the
פרק, perek, the difference between רבית ribbis and נשך. neshech. From Michael's
perspective it's נשך, neshech, because he doesn't have money, he's going to
have to pay extra because he needs cash now. Okay, or because
he needs beer now, but his absence of cash means that he
has to pay extra. From my perspective it's not so much of
a gain because I could have made the same money by just
having waited six months.
But it does seem from the perspective of the seller that the
definition of רבית ribbis also depends upon the stability of the market,
right? It's because it's the same price, the same price now as
later...
No, later it's going to be worth a dollar and a half.
I'm selling it to Michael now at the later price.
Essentially you're saying I'll do you a favor Michael and let you
have the beer now, but I wouldn't be selling it now I'd
be waiting until I could sell it at a higher price.
Exactly, that's a nice way of saying it, exactly. You know, you
want the beer now, I could just as easily wait six months
and sell it in six months from now, right? That's I think
that puts it a little bit sharper, right? So I'm doing you
the favor, I'm giving it to you now, I could have just
held on to it and waited for it. I don't need your
money, right? And I don't need whatever.
And the seller who's buying it right now is going to have
to sell it at a lower price because six months from now
it's going to go up. Right. But he needs the money, so
he's going to buy it now...
But רב פפא's Rav Pappa saying I don't need the money.
Right, the seller doesn't need the money.
Yeah. But the buyer needs the beer.
The buyer needs the beer. Right, he the buyer needs the beer,
he wants to buy it at low prices, but he doesn't have
the cash to buy it. So he wants so yeah.
So let's say really let's say, you know, I have a contract,
someone would buy it like, you know, six months from now at
that price. Right. And they say okay if you want it now
buy me out from that contract, is that any different?
I have to think that one through but that might be okay.
Anyway, the point that I want... let's get back to this. So
the point here is so this is a case where I just
set the price. The price was a dollar and a half a
barrel. Okay, I just set the price. So that's the case of
תרשא. tarsha. We didn't say at higher than today's prices because you're
going to pay later. But here's the point. So does רב פפא
Rav Pappa disagree with רב נחמן? Rav Nachman Because רב נחמן Rav
Nachman seems to say all תרשא tarsha is okay and רב פפא
Rav Pappa seems to say no, not all תרשא, tarsha, my type
of תרשא. tarsha. But תוספות Tosafot says later no no no here's
the difference. We could פסקן pasken like רב נחמן and not like
רב פפא. Rav Pappa. How's that possible? Because he says in רב
פפא Rav Pappa the question is what's considered a case of קץ,
katz, of being right, of being that it's clearly an extra charge.
If the market price is set at a dollar, I don't have
to say any words. If I'm saying to Michael you're going to
pay me when are you going to pay me in six months?
Okay, the price is a dollar and a half. That is no
longer תרשא, tarsha, that is a case of קץ, katz, because everybody
knows that the price right now is a dollar. So רב פפא
Rav Pappa is saying nevertheless even in my situation it's okay because
I'm doing him the favor. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara says I'm
sorry, he's still paying extra. All right, but you could so we
could say we reject רב פפא Rav Pappa but we could still
say for רב נחמן if there's no clear set price and you
know that this isn't in contrast to then that could be okay.
Okay, so we can פסקן pasken like רב נחמן when there's no
clear set price but not like רב פפא Rav Pappa when there's
a clear set market price.
What is תרשא? tarsha?
What's the definition of תרשא?
tarsha? תרשא tarsha is like a higher payment that's not being made
explicit. A non-explicit higher payment. A higher
cost, higher price. What?
Even though usually they call whoever the second person was, they call
his תרשא? tarsha?
Right, so that's the point. Sometimes it's not really תרשא tarsha because
it's קץ, katz, right?
But they call it a תרשא.
tarsha. Yeah. Well, yeah. But the point is you're not explicitly saying
the words. תוספות's Tosfos point is you could call it תרשא tarsha
because you're not saying the words, but it could be not the
same type of תרשא tarsha because it's explicit based on context.
Right. Exactly. Okay, let's take another case like this. Okay, we're the
גמרא Gemara is actually going to פסקן pasken in a second Michael
if we could get there. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. says like
this, okay, אמר
רב חמא, Amar Rav Hama, תרשא דידי פרי שרי. tarsha didi pari
shari. I don't know about רב פפא Rav Pappa like yeah you
made a good point with רב פפא, Rav Pappa, it's from
he's not gaining anything but the buyer is still losing out, so
that's not allowed. But my תרשא's tarsha okay. Why? מאי טעמא? Now
what was his case? His case was the following, a very interesting
case. Okay, Michael here
regularly goes and he you know and he travels into Manhattan. I
don't go there, that's a foreign country for me. Okay, and he
makes now... He's going to ahead and take my wares and go
bring them into Manhattan and he's going to sell them and they
go for more, they go here they go for dollar, there they
go for two dollars. So he's going to buy them from me,
sell them there, and make a profit, make him a two dollar.
Okay, but what he actually does is, he says to me, he's
going to buy them from me at two dollars and sell them
in Manhattan for two dollars. So like, you know, that's like, you're
not such a good businessman, Michael, why are you doing that? You're
doing that because once you get that cash, you're only going to
pay me my money later, right? They
go for a dollar here, you're going to pay me my, you're
going to pay me two dollars for it later, when you after
you sell it there in Manhattan. But what are you going to
get out of it? You bought it, you sold it. No, because
once you get that cash in Manhattan, you can pick up some
cheap merchandise, some, you know, somewhere there and bring it back and
sell it here at a profit. You got the whole thing? So
he's taking my object, selling it there. He's going to give me
the price that he's selling it for there. But he's going to
make a profit because he's going in the interim, he's going to
use that money, buy some cheap merchandise, bring it back with him,
sell it here at three dollars and then he's going to give
me two and he's going to have profited one. That's the deal.
Okay. Now, the point is if you were selling it as my
merchandise, you know, whatever, something like that, fine, you haven't, you haven't
paid me any interest or whatever. You're just, I just make you
my שליח shaliach to sell it there for two dollars. But we
didn't do that. We said you bought it now, here it's going
for a dollar and you're going to pay me when you come
back from Manhattan, you're going to pay me two dollars. Okay, even
though now it goes for a dollar. So that sounds like a
higher fee for later payment.
You could ask them in Manhattan that...
well, that's true. So let's see why he says it's permissible.
Did they say anything about what to pay you now?
Yes, you did. Oh yeah. We know it goes for a dollar
here and goes for two dollars there. And that's a case similar
to this כץ. katz. Nobody is saying those words but we all
know that. And how you ask me how much are you going
to sell it to me for? Two bucks. Okay, and you're even
though you're going to pay me in six months when you get
back from Manhattan, two bucks. Okay, so you buy it for two
bucks, whatever the whole thing. So that's a case of תרשא tarsha
with sort of like a כץ katz based on fixed prices.
Wouldn't that be a case of תרשא tarsha you're explicit about what
you're...
no, you're not saying oh if you buy pay me now it's
a dollar. You're saying when are you going to pay me when
you get back? Okay, how much? Okay, six dollars... I mean two
dollars. Okay, so now תרשא לדידי ודאי שרי מאי טעמא ניחא
להו דליפקא ברשותי. tarsha ledidi vadai shari mai ta'ama nicha lehu delifka
birshuti. It's good now the point is here's the other point that
wasn't said which sort of should make it clear why it's okay.
I, what I basically do is I insure the product that Michael
is bringing to Manhattan and I say to him if something happens
and that product gets destroyed on the way, I'll reimburse you for
it even though he has technically bought it from me but of
course now you understand. So he hasn't really so much bought it
from me. To some degree he's taking my product to Manhattan to
sell because I'm insuring it, right? So I'm going to reimburse him.
So that's basically what רבא says that because he's basically, I'm insuring
him for that, to some degree it's not like he's purchased it
and he hasn't paid me the money yet, to some degree it's
still sort of my product that he's just going to sell over
there. Okay. Wouldn't it make it worse?
Because like you know why
you took my product if you really just I hadn't sold it
to all, you took my product, you sold it, you got two
dollars. At that stage that was my two dollars. So basically what
you did is you borrowed those two dollars from me, you used
it to buy product, you came back and you paid me two
dollars. That would be totally okay, right? Totally right, right? So the
only thing that problematizes it is that you've bought it from me.
אבל אמר מר קא יהבו שכר מרבך. aval amar mar ka yahavu
sechar merivach.
What are you talking about? I'm giving you my product to sell
for me and I'm telling you after you sell it you can
make use, you can borrow that money and pay me it back
when you get back, when you get back from. Totally okay. All
right anyway so he says that's effectively what's happening here. Okay. So
מאי טעמא ניחא להו דליפקא ברשותי. mai ta'ama nicha lehu delifka birshuti.
It's good now Michael benefits that everybody considers it to be my
product. דכל היכא דאזלי שבקי להו מכסא dechol heicha de'azli shavki lehu
machsa because everybody knows he's going to bring it into Manhattan and
they normally would charge an import tax but he says oh wait
I have Dov Lando's product oh you have Dov Lando's product okay
no tax for you. So that's basically what he says right? I'm
a well known you know I'm a big rabbinic figure so people
don't charge him tax. ונקטי להו שוקא venakti lehu shuka and they
also give him the right of first sale. He comes to the
marketplace and everybody and he gets the right to sell his product
first. So he benefits from it. Now תוספות Tosfos why do you
have to say he benefits from it? Once we explained that I'm
insuring the product until it's sold that should be enough to consider
it like it's basically my product. So therefore what's the problem at
all? Okay so תוספות says no the problem here is that Michael
is still doing me a favor. Why is Michael doing me a
favor? He's schlepping it to Manhattan and selling it for two dollars
whereas if we sold it here. I only get a dollar. So
what am I doing to pay Michael for that favor, for שלעפינג
schlepping it and getting me two dollars for it rather than one?
So effectively, what, you know what I'm doing to pay Michael for
that favor, what am I doing to pay Michael for that favor?
Later. I'm lending him the two dollars when he, after he sells
it. Right? You see, right? So that's that favor he did me
is a type of a ריבית. ribbis Michael basically says, I will
take your product, sell it in a place that I can get
a higher price for it on the condition that I get to
use that money, you know, at that place and I'll pay you
back when I come back. So basically he's giving me the service
of bringing my product to a higher market in exchange for me
lending him the money. So so that's what makes this a possible
ריבית ribbis issue. That is counterbalanced by the fact that Michael gets
a, you know, that people that he gets these benefits because it's
known to be my product and not his. They don't charge him
tax and they give him the first right to sell, etc. Okay,
so anyway, that's a very complicated case but he says that's why
it's okay. Anyway, let's go on to the let's see how the
גמרא Gemara concludes. והלכתא, Vehilchasa, the הלכה halacha is okay. First of
all כרב חמא. keRav Chama. So first of all the הלכה halacha
is like רב חמא, Rav Chama, which is that was this last
case. This special case, this is not considered, this is considered a
higher price, but it's not considered a type of a
ריבית. ribbis והלכתא כרבי אליעזר Vehilchasa keRabbi Eliezer and we rule like
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that said ריבית קצוצה יוצאה בדיינין. ribbis ketutza
yotza bedayanin. That was implicit in the previous discussion. Okay, that when
it's an explicit ריבית ribbis. in the contract, you can retrieve it
through the court. והלכתא כרב ינאי דאמר מלויהן מלו דמיהן. Vehilchasa keRav
Yannai de'amar malihan mali dameihan. So we're going back to an earlier,
remember when רב ינאי Rav Yannai says if you sort of pre-sell
money and then whatever now the prices are higher, pre-sell wheat and
then when I pay you back, I don't pay you back in
wheat, but I pay you back in money. So you gave me
a thousand dollars for wheat now and when it's time to pay
and the wheat is worth more, instead of giving you the wheat,
I give you twelve hundred dollars based on its current value. Right?
So that looks a lot like ריבית. And רב ינאי Rav Yannai
said no, the same way you could deliver the wheat, you could
deliver the money. And תוספות here says by the way that we
can rule both like רב חמא Rav Chama and like רב נחמן
about טרשא. tarsha. That's why I said it before. If there's nothing,
no explicit things that are said about what if you pay me
now and there's no explicit clear market price, then I can set
a higher price knowing you're going to pay me later. And that's
just considered the price. But if I explicitly say it'll be less
now, more later, or there's a clear market price, that's when it's
like קצוצה, ketutza, that's when it's problematic.
But the גמרא didn't say הלכתא כרב נחמן, hilchasa keRav Nachman, we
just know that.
Yeah, תוספות says it based on other discussions. Yeah, in other discussions.
Let's look at the next משנה. mishna.
Boy, I thought we'd get ahead. מכר לו את השדה ונתן לו
מקצת דמים ואמר לו אימת שתביא שאר מעות הוי מעות ופירות שלך.
Machar lo es hasadeh venasan lo miktzas damim ve'amar lo eimas shetavi
sh'ar ma'os havi ma'os ufitu shelcha. Okay, when the גמרא is easier
to understand and you want to talk about how you want to
talk about
practical application... If you don't understand it... Exactly! If you don't understand,
how can you get through more ground? Okay, מכר לו את השדה
ונתן לו מקצת דמים. machar lo es hasadeh venasan lo miktzas damim.
Okay,
so I sell Michael my field and it's for a thousand dollars
and he gives me a hundred. Down payment? Well, we'll see. Let's
say it's a partial well, that's will depend. Okay, hold on. He
gives me a hundred and I say, you know Michael, as soon
and today is January 1. Whenever you get me the remainder, the
remaining nine hundred,
retroactively, you know, it'll be the sale is effective as of today
and you can come and collect the field and actually, you know,
take possession of it when you pay me the balance. You owe
me another nine hundred, but it's effective as of today or it'll
be effective retroactively. Okay, in that case אסור. assur. That's forbidden. What's
forbidden about that? That seems like a pretty normal thing. So what's
going to be forbidden is who is going to benefit from the
fruit for the next six months while we're waiting for Michael to
pay the balance. So let's think this through. Let's say I'm going
to eat the fruit okay of the field. Then Michael pays me
later okay, retroactively the sale took place as of today. So he's
paying you ריבית. So basically because he waited to pay me the
balance, I was getting the fruit of the field which was his
field retroactively. Okay, so I shouldn't eat the fruit. Great. Let's have
Michael eat the fruit because retroactively it's going to be his field.
Aha, but here's what's going to happen. Michael is not going to
come up with the nine hundred dollars. And if you don't come
up with the nine hundred dollars, then the sale is בטל batel
and I give you back the hundred. So you've now been eating
fruit of a field that now we find out wasn't yours okay
and in the interim I was holding onto a hundred dollars of
yours. So now we will view it as your eating of that
fruit while I'm holding onto a hundred dollars of yours was I
was giving you ריבית for the fact that I was holding onto
that payment. So therefore there's no way since we don't know which
way it'll come out, right, we don't know who will it be,
since the money is partially paid and we don't know in the
end whether the sale will be final or not final, we don't
know who is the one that's borrowing money so that it would
be you know and so that and therefore the other one could
be eating the ריבית of you know depending on who's borrowing the
money.
But if I pay you it's all okay?
If
if it worked out that you ate the fruit and you paid
me it would be okay.
Yeah, so that's the assumption of the משנה, mishnah though the גמרא
will deal with other scenarios. But then it means that the מקח
mekach was בטל, battel, and if the מקח mekach was בטל, battel,
the only way we conceptualize the money is as a loan. That
wasn't how it was, why it was given, but that's the way
we conceptualize it.
If no one eats the food and we explicitly agree it's totally
fine, right?
Yes. Okay. הלוהו על שדהו ואמר לו אם אי אתה נותן לי
מכאן ועד שלוש שנים הרי היא שלי הרי היא שלו. Havehu al
sado ve'amar lo im i attah nosen li mikan ve'ad shalosh shanim
harei hi sheli harei hi shelo. Now let's say I went ahead,
totally different story. I went ahead, and this is like predatory lending.
I went ahead and I said to Michael, okay, Michael, you want
to borrow a thousand dollars? Fine, but here's the deal: you have
three years to pay me up, and if you don't pay me
up in three years, I'm seizing your field, which happens to be
worth fifteen hundred dollars. Okay, yeah, it's predatory lending. Okay, so that
is הרי היא שלו, harei hi shelo, that's okay. וכך היה ביתוס
בן זונין עושה על פי חכמים. Vechach hayah Baisos ben Zonin oseh
al pi Chachamim. And ביתוס בן זונין, Baisos ben Zonin, who was
this businessman who's always coming up, this is what he would do:
he would lend money, give the borrower a certain time to pay,
and if not, he would designate the property that he'd be entitled
to take in collection of that loan, even though that property would
be worth more. So the question is why is that? It also
seems you could say, well, there's a way in which it could
work out that they don't lose the property, like the צד אחד
בריבית, tzad echad b'ribbis, right? If you pay the loan you don't
lose the
property, yeah. But if it works out the other way, you're getting
something of greater value, maybe it's going back to the earlier discussion
that since that's a piece of property, maybe we're just setting the
price of the property at a thousand even though Michael could probably
get fifteen hundred. So it's not exactly clear why that case is
okay, but yes, we'll see the first part of the משנה.
mishnah Well, I was going to ask the opposite: why isn't this
exactly what it means to have a lien on a piece of
property?
Well, because a lien on a piece of property would only allow
me to collect up the value based on the market price, and
here we have designated that I'm entitled to the entire plot of
land even if you could get much more for that in the
open market.
And might get much less.
Yeah, it could be, but I don't think that's part of what
makes this allowed. It could be that it would be clear that
this is going to be worth more than that amount and nevertheless
it's allowed.
Let's see the real estate market is.
Alright, so that's fine. Let's take a look at the גמרא. So
the גמרא says מי אוכל פירות, Mi ochal peiros, who eats the
fruit? Which is, so this is, we're going to give some opinions
and then we'll work it all out. רב הונא אמר מוכר אוכל
פירות. Rav Huna amar mocher ochal peiros. In this case where it
was a down payment and so on.
I thought you
weren't allowed to do it. I know, so we'll take a look,
just have patience. The seller eats the fruit. רבנן
אמרי משלשין את הפירות. Rabanan amri mishalshin es hapeiros. So that's the
easiest answer: have a third party hold on to them and then
you give it to who retroactively wound up was the owner of
the field. That's the easiest thing, have it being held by a
third party. ולא פליגי. Velo peligi. הא
דאמר ליה לכי מייתית קני, Ha de'amar lei lichi maysis kani, if
you say that not when you give me the balance you will
own it retroactively as of today. If you say when you give
me the balance you'll own it then. So that's a down payment,
right? So you don't own it now, you'll own it when you
give me the balance. Oh, so if you'll own it when you
give me the balance, who eats the פירות peiros in the interim?
Me, the seller, because it's mine until you've given it, and then
it's מותר. muttar. Right. So הא דאמר ליה לכי מייתית קני הא
דאמר ליה
לכי מייתית קני מעכשיו. Ha de'amar lei lichi maysis kani ha de'amar
lei lichi maysis kani me'achshav. But if you say when you give
it you'll own it retroactively as of now, then we don't know
how it's going to work out, whether it will be a sale,
won't be a sale, and therefore we don't know who to give
the פירות peiros to, so you have to give it to a
third party. Okay.
And then it would be permissible too?
It would be permissible in the משנה if you gave it to
a third party. Okay. תני רב ספרא בריבית דבי רבי חייא. Tani
Rav Safra b'ribbis d'vei Rebbi Chiya. רב ספרא Rav Safra taught in
when he was in the ברייתא braisa about ריבית in when, you
know, רבי חייא Rebbi Chiya is the author of, the editor of
the תוספתא. Tosefta. פעמים ששניהם מותרים, Pe'amim sheshneihem mutarin, there's times where
both the מוכר mocher and the לוקח lokeach are allowed to eat
the fruit. פעמים ששניהם אסורים, Pe'amim sheshneihem asurin, there's time when they're
both not allowed, which is our משנה. פעמים שהמוכר מותר ולוקח אסור,
Pe'amim shehamocher muttar velokeach assur, sometimes the seller can eat and not
the לוקח. lokeach. פעמים שהלוקח מותר ומוכר אסור, Pe'amim shehalokeach muttar umocher
assur, and sometimes it's the opposite. Okay, and he didn't spell it
out. עני רבה בתריה. Ani Raba basrei. Raba says wait wait I
can figure this out, I know can figure out the four possibilities.
Here's what they're going to be. פעמים ששניהם מותרים, Pe'amim sheshneihem mutarin,
when can they both eat from it? דאמר ליה קני כשיעור זוזך.
De'amar lei kani kishi'ur zuzach. Michael gives me the hundred dollars and
I say great, you own now ten percent of the land. So
now you can eat ten percent of the fruit and I eat
the other ninety percent of fruit. Wonderful. פעמים ששניהם אסורים, Pe'amim sheshneihem
asurin, that's our משנה. דאמר ליה לכי מייתית קני מעכשיו. De'amar lei
lichi maysis kani me'achshav. That when you give me the balance you
own it retroactively. So there we both have some of each other's
money and we don't know the way it's going to work out,
we don't know who the borrower is going to be and who
the lender is going to be and therefore neither of us can
eat the fruit.
Okay. פעמים מוכר מותר ולוקח אסור, Pe'amim mocher muttar velokeach assur, sometimes
the seller's allowed to. דאמר ליה לכי מייתית קני. De'amar lei lichi
maysis kani. When you pay, then you will own it. Okay, so
therefore in that case where you'll only own it later, so in
the interim it's all mine, so of course I eat the fruit.
It's all the seller's. פעמים שהלוקח מותר מוכר אסור, Pe'amim shehalokeach muttar
mocher assur, and the time it's the first.
דאמר ליה קני מעכשיו. De'amar lei kani me'achshav. Right now you own
it, end of story. Okay, how about the nine hundred dollars? זוזיי
ליהוו הלוואה בך. Zuzai lehevei halva'ah bach. Oh, that's just a loan.
Now you owe me the nine hundred dollars, but it's not conditional
on the sale. A hundred percent it's yours right now. So that
case, hundred percent it's yours right now. Who eats the fruit? The
לוקח. lokeach. Okay, and he just owns and he just owes me
the rest of the money. מאן תנא שניהם אסורים man tanna sheneichem
asurim and let's just end this, I don't know, מאן תנא שניהם
אסורים, man tanna sheneichem asurim, who is who is the author of
our משנה that if it works that both are אסור asur because
you don't know which way it's going to work out? אמר רב
הונא בריה דרב יהושע דלא כרבי יהודה, amar Rav Huna breih deRav
Yehoshua delo keRabbi Yehuda, not like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאי כרבי
יהודה אמר צד אחד ברבית מותר. de'i keRabbi Yehuda amar tzad echad
beribbis mutar. We had this before, right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
as long as one of the two ways it works out it
won't be a problem, if it happens to happen happens to have
happened and happens to have happened the other way, so, so okay,
it's not ריבית because it didn't have to happen that way. So
even if in the end of the day I was eating the
fruit because I was assuming whom, I'm the seller, I was eating,
no, let's say Michael was eating the fruit because he was assuming
that it was going to be his field retroactively, and in the
end he couldn't come up with the money and it was בטל
batel and then he got his hundred dollars back, so in the
end he ate fruit and I was holding on to his hundred
dollars. Since that didn't have to happen that way, even though it
did, it's not considered to be ריבית. Okay, that's what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would say but our משנה says otherwise. Good, we'll pick
up here tomorrow.